Fifty-four percent of the world's population
54 % من سكان العالم
lives in our cities.
يعيشون في مدننا
In developing countries,
في الدول النامية
one third of that population
ثلث السكان
is living in slums.
يعيشون في العشوائيات.
Seventy-five percent of global energy consumption
75 % من استهلاك الطاقة العالمي
occurs in our cities,
يحدث في مدننا،
and 80 percent of gas emissions
و 80% من الانبعاثات الغازية
that cause global warming
التي تسبب الاحتباس الحراري
come from our cities.
تخرج من مدننا
So things that you and I might think about
لذلك فالأشياء التي أنا أو أنتم يمكن أن نفكر فيها
as global problems,
كالمشاكل العالمية،
like climate change, the energy crisis
مثل التغير المناخي، أو أزمة الطاقة
or poverty,
أو الفقر،
are really, in many ways, city problems.
حقًا - وبعدة طرق - مشاكل المدينة.
They will not be solved
والتي لن يتم حلها
unless people who live in cities,
إلا لو أن الناس الذين يسكنون المدن،
like most of us,
كمعظمنا،
actually start doing a better job,
يبدأون حقًا القيام بعمل أفضل،
because right now, we are not doing a very good one.
لأنه حتي الأن، لم نقم بهذا العمل الجيد.
And that becomes very clear
ولقد أصبح هذا الأمر جليًا
when we look into three aspects of city life:
عندما ننظر إلى الجوانب الثلاثة لحياة المدينة:
first, our citizens' willingness to engage
أولاً، رغبة مواطنينا في المشاركة
with democratic institutions;
مع المؤسسات الديموقراطية.
second, our cities' ability to really include
ثانيًا، مدننا وقدرتها على احتواء
all of their residents;
كل المقيمين بها.
and lastly, our own ability
وأخيرًا، قدرتنا الخاصة
to live fulfilling and happy lives.
لكي نعيش حياة مرضية وسعيدة.
When it comes to engagement,
وعندما نتحدث عن المشاركة،
the data is very clear.
البيانات واضحة جدًا.
Voter turnout around the world
إن إقبال الناخبين حول العالم
peaked in the late '80s,
وصل ذروته في أواخر الثمانينات،
and it has been declining at a pace
ثم انخفض بوتيرة
that we have never seen before,
لم نرها من قبل،
and if those numbers are bad at the national level,
وإن كانت هذه الأرقام سيئة على المستوى الوطني،
at the level of our cities,
فعلى مستوى مدننا،
they are just dismal.
فهي كئيبة للغاية.
In the last two years,
في آخر عامين،
two of the world's most consolidated,
اثنان من أكثر دول العالم ثباتًا،
oldest democracies, the U.S. and France,
أقدم الديموقراطيات، أميركا وفرنسا،
held nationwide municipal elections.
أقاموا انتخابات البلدية الوطنية.
In France, voter turnout hit a record low.
في فرنسا، إقبال الناخبين حقق مستوى متدني.
Almost 40 percent of voters decided
حوالي 40% من الناخبين قرروا
not to show up.
ألا يشاركوا.
In the U.S., the numbers were even scarier.
وفي أمريكا، الرقم كان مخيفًا جدًا.
In some American cities,
في بعض المدن الأمريكية،
voter turnout was close to five percent.
إقبال الناخبين كان حوالي 5%.
I'll let that sink in for a second.
دعونا نمعن النظر للحظة.
We're talking about democratic cities
نحن نتحدث عن مدن ديمقراطية
in which 95 percent of people
فيها 95% من الناس
decided that it was not important
قرروا أنه ليس من المهم
to elect their leaders.
أن ينتخبوا قادتهم.
The city of L.A., a city of four million people,
في " لوس أنجلوس "، مدينة بها 4 مليون نسمة،
elected its mayor with just a bit over 200,000 votes.
انتخبوا العمدة بحوالي 200 ألف صوت.
That was the lowest turnout the city had seen
وكان هذا أقل معدل للإقبال شاهدته المدينة
in 100 years.
في 100 عام.
Right here, in my city of Rio,
وهنا، في مدينتي " ريو "،
in spite of mandatory voting,
على الرغم من أن التصويت إلزاميًا،
almost 30 percent of the voting population
حوالي 30% من السكان الذين لهم حق التصويت
chose to either annul their votes
اختاروا إما إن يبطلوا أصواتهم
or stay home and pay a fine
أو يبقوا في المنزل ويدفعوا الغرامة
in the last mayoral elections.
في انتخابات البلدية الأخيرة.
When it comes to inclusiveness,
عندما نتحدث بشمولية،
our cities are not the best cases of success either,
مدننا ليست أفضل حالات النجاح أيضًا،
and again, you don't need to look very far
ومجددًا، لن تحتاجوا للنظر بعيدًا
in order to find proof of that.
لكي تجد الدليل علي هذا.
The city of Rio is incredibly unequal.
مدينة "ريو" غير متساوية بشكل لا يصدق.
This is Leblon.
هذه "ليبلون".
Leblon is the city's richest neighborhood.
"ليبلون" الحي الأغنى في المدينة.
And this is Complexo do Alemão.
وهذه "كومبليكسو دو أليماو".
This is where over 70,000
التي يعيش بها أكثر من 70 ألف
of the city's poorest residents live.
من فقراء المدينة.
Leblon has an HDI, a Human Development Index,
"ليبلون" لها مؤشر تنمية بشرية،
of .967.
يساوي 0.967
That is higher than Norway, Switzerland
وذلك أعلي من النرويج، أو سويسرا
or Sweden.
أو السويد.
Complexo do Alemão has an HDI of .711.
"كومبليكسو دو أليماو" لها مؤشر تنمية بشرية = 0.711
It sits somewhere in between the HDI
تقع في مكان ما بين مؤشر التنمية البشرية
of Algeria and Gabon.
للجزائر والجابون.
So Rio, like so many cities across the global South,
لذلك "ريو"، مثل العديد من المدن في جنوب العالم،
is a place where you can go from northern Europe
هي المكان الذي يمكنك به الذهاب من شمال أوروبا
to sub-Saharan Africa
إلى الصحراء الأفريقية الكبرى
in the space of 30 minutes.
في مسافة 30 دقيقة.
If you drive, that is.
إذا ركبت سيارة، ستكون كذلك.
If you take public transit, it's about two hours.
وإذا ركبت المواصلات العامة، ستستغرق حوالي ساعتين.
And lastly, perhaps most importantly,
وفي النهاية، ربما أن الأكثر أهمية،
cities, with the incredible wealth
المدن، وما بها من ثروات غير معقولة
of relations that they enable,
من العلاقات المتاحة،
could be the ideal places for human happiness
يمكن أن تكون الأماكن المثالية لسعادة البشر
to flourish.
لكي تزدهر.
We like being around people.
نحن نحب أن نكون محاطين بالناس.
We are social animals.
نحن كائنات اجتماعية.
Instead, countries where urbanization
وبالرغم من ذلك، الدول التي بها التحضر
has already peaked seem to be the very countries
قد وصل إلى ذروته تبدو أنها الدول الأكثر
in which cities have stopped making us happy.
التي توقفت مدنها عن جعلنا سعداء.
The United States population has suffered
إن سكان أمريكا قد عانوا
from a general decrease in happiness
من نقص عام في السعادة
for the past three decades,
في آخر 3 عقود،
and the main reason is this.
والسبب الرئيسي هو أن
The American way of building cities
الأسلوب الأمريكي في بناء المدن
has caused good quality public spaces
تسبب في أن النوعية الجيدة من الأماكن العامة
to virtually disappear in many,
على وشك الاختفاء في العديد،
many American cities,
العديد من المدن الأمريكية،
and as a result, they have seen
وكنتيجة لذلك، فقد لاحظوا
a decline of relations,
انخفاضًا في العلاقات،
of the things that make us happy.
والأشياء التي تجعلنا سعداء.
Many studies show an increase
العديد من الدراسات أظهرت زيادة
in solitude and a decrease in solidarity,
في العزلة ونقص في التضامن،
honesty, and social and civic participation.
والأمانة والمشاركة المجتمعية والمدنية.
So how do we start building cities
ولذلك كيف نبدأ في بناء المدن
that make us care?
التي تجعلنا مهتمين ؟
Cities that value their most important asset:
المدن التي قيمة أهم ممتلكاتها:
the incredible diversity
هو التنوع غير المعقول
of the people who live in them?
للسكان الذين يعيشون فيها؟
Cities that make us happy?
المدن التي تجعلنا سعداء؟
Well, I believe that if we want to change
حسنا، أنا أؤمن بأننا إذا أردنا أن نغيير
what our cities look like,
مما تبدو عليه مدننا،
then we really have to change
فيتوجب علينا أن نغيير
the decision-making processes
عملية صنع القرار
that have given us the results that we have right now.
التي أعطتنا النتائج التي لدينا الآن.
We need a participation revolution,
نحتاج إلى ثورة في المشاركة،
and we need it fast.
ونحتاج إليها سريعًا.
The idea of voting as our only exercise in citizenship
فكرة أن التصويت هو النشاط الوحيد في المواطنة
does not make sense anymore.
لا معنى لها بعد الآن.
People are tired of only being treated
الناس تعبوا من أن تتم معاملتهم فقط
as empowered individuals every few years
بسلطة فردية كل بضع سنوات
when it's time to delegate that power
وعندما يحين الوقت لكي تفوض تلك السلطة
to someone else.
إلى شخص آخر.
If the protests that swept Brazil
لو أن المظاهرات التي اجتاحت "البرازيل"
in June 2013 have taught us anything,
في يونيو 2013 علمتنا شىء ما،
it's that every time we try
إنه في كل مرة نحاول
to exercise our power
أن نمارس سلطتنا
outside of an electoral context,
خارج السياق الانتخابي،
we are beaten up, humiliated or arrested.
يتم ضربنا أو إهانتنا أو اعتقالنا.
And this needs to change,
وهذا الأمر يحتاج إلى تغيير،
because when it does,
لأنه عندما يحدث،
not only will people re-engage
لن يقوم الناس فقط بإعادة تعيين
with the structures of representation,
نظم التمثيل،
but also complement these structures
لكن أيضًا تكملة هذه النظم
with direct, effective, and collective decision making,
بصنع القرار المباشر والمؤثر والمجمع عليه،
decision making of the kind
صنع القرار من النوع
that attacks inequality
الذي يهاجم عدم المساواة
by its very inclusive nature,
بطبيعتها الشاملة جدًا،
decision making of the kind
صنع القرار من النوع
that can change our cities
الذي يمكن أن يغير مدننا
into better places for us to live.
إلى أماكن أفضل لكي نعيش فيها.
But there is a catch, obviously:
ولكن هناك شاهد، بوضوح:
Enabling widespread participation
إتاحة المشاركة بشكل واسع الانتشار
and redistributing power
وإعادة توزيع السلطة
can be a logistical nightmare,
يمكن أن يكون كابوس إداري،
and there's where technology can play
وهنا يمكن للتكنولوجيا أن تلعب
an incredibly helpful role,
دورًا مفيدًا ومدهشًا،
by making it easier for people to organize,
بأن تجعل الأمر أسهل للناس لينظموا،
communicate and make decisions
ويتواصلوا ويصنعوا قراراتهم
without having to be in the same room
دون الحاجة إلى أن يكونوا في نفس الحجرة
at the same time.
في نفس الوقت.
Unfortunately for us,
ولسوء حظنا،
when it comes to fostering democratic processes,
عندما نأتي إلى تدعيم العمليات الديمقراطية،
our city governments have not used technology
حكومات مدننا لم تستخدم التكنولوجيا
to its full potential.
بكامل إرادتها.
So far, most city governments have been effective
حتى الآن، معظم حكومات المدن كانت متأثرة
at using tech to turn citizens into human sensors
باستخدام التكنولوجيا لتحويل المواطنين إلى أجهزة استشعار بشرية
who serve authorities with data on the city:
تمد السلطات ببيانات عن المدينة:
potholes, fallen trees or broken lamps.
الحُفر أو الشجر المتساقط أو المصابيح المحطمة.
They have also, to a lesser extent,
وقاموا أيضًا، وبدرجة أقل،
invited people to participate in improving
بدعوة الناس إلى المشاركة في تنمية
the outcome of decisions
الناتج من القرارات
that were already made for them,
التي قرروها من أنفسهم،
just like my mom when I was eight
فقط مثل أمي عندما كنت في الثامنة
and she told me that I had a choice:
وأخبرتني أنني أملك الخيار:
I had to be in bed by 8 p.m.,
يجب أن أستعد للنوم الثامنة مساءً،
but I could choose my pink pajamas or my blue pajamas.
ولكني استطيع أن اختار بين البيجامة الوردية أو الزرقاء
That's not participation,
هذه ليست مشاركة،
and in fact, governments have not been very good
وفي الحقيقة، الحكومات لم تكن جيدة
at using technology to enable participation
في استخدام التكنولوجيا لإتاحة المشاركة
on what matters —
علي أية حال
the way we allocate our budget,
الطريقة التي نحدد بها ميزانتنا،
the way we occupy our land,
والطريقة التي نشغل بها أرضنا،
and the way we manage our natural resources.
والطريقة التي ندير بها مواردنا الطبيعية.
Those are the kinds of decisions
تلك هي أنواع القرارات
that can actually impact global problems
التي يمكنها أن تؤثر في المشاكل العالمية فعلًا
that manifest themselves in our cities.
التي تظهر في مدننا.
The good news is,
الأخبار الجيدة هي،
and I do have good news to share with you,
وأنا لدي أخبار جيدة لأشاركها معكم،
we don't need to wait for governments to do this.
لا نحتاج لانتظار الحكومات لتفعل ذلك.
I have reason to believe
عندي سبب لأؤمن
that it's possible for citizens to build
أنه من الممكن للمواطنين أن يبنوا
their own structures of participation.
نظم المشاركة الخاصة بهم.
Three years ago, I cofounded an organization
منذ 3 سنوات، قمت بإنشاء منظمة
called Meu Rio,
اسمها "ميو ريو"
and we make it easier for people in the city of Rio
وجعلنا من السهل للناس في مدينة "ريو"
to organize around causes and places
تنظيم القضايا والأماكن
that they care about in their own city,
التي يهتمون به في مدينتهم،
and have an impact on those causes and places
وأن يكون لهم تأثير علي هذه القضايا والأماكن
every day.
كل يوم.
In these past three years, Meu Rio grew
في هذه الثلاث سنوات السابقة، "ميو ريو" نمت
to a network of 160,000 citizens of Rio.
إلى شبكة من 160 ألف مواطن من "ريو".
About 40 percent of those members are young people
حوالي 40% من الأعضاء شباب
aged 20 to 29.
من عمر 20 إلى 29.
That is one in every 15 young people
وهذا واحد من كل 15 شاب
of that age in Rio today.
في هذا العمر في "ريو" اليوم.
Amongst our members is this adorable little girl,
ومن بين أعضائنا هذه الفتاة الصغيرة المحبوبة،
Bia, to your right,
"بيا"، علي يمينكم،
and Bia was just 11 years old
و"بيا" كانت 11 عام فقط
when she started a campaign using one of our tools
عندما بدأت حملة باستخدام أحد أدواتنا
to save her model public school from demolition.
لكي تحمي مدرستها العامة من الهدم.
Her school actually ranks among the best
في الواقع، تم ترتيب مدرستها بين أفضل
public schools in the country,
المدارس العامة في البلد،
and it was going to be demolished
وكانت في طريقها ليتم هدمها
by the Rio de Janeiro state government
بواسطه حكومة ولاية "ريو دي جانيرو"
to build, I kid you not,
لكي يبنوا، وأنا لا أمزح،
a parking lot for the World Cup
ساحة انتظار للسيارات لكأس العالم
right before the event happened.
قبل وقوع الحدث مباشرةً.
Bia started a campaign, and we even watched
بدأت "بيا" حملة، كنا نشاهد
her school 24/7 through webcam monitoring,
مدرستها سبعة أيام أسبوعيًا، 24 ساعة يوميًا من خلال كاميرات الويب،
and many months afterwards,
وبعد عدة شهور،
the government changed their minds.
غيرت الحكومة رأيها.
Bia's school stayed in place.
مدرسة "بيا" ستظل بمكانها.
There's also Jovita.
هناك أيضًا "جوفيتا".
She's an amazing woman whose daughter
هي المرأة المذهلة التي تاهت ابنتها
went missing about 10 years ago,
منذ 10 أعوام.
and since then, she has been looking
ومنذ ذلك الوقت، ظلت تبحث
for her daughter.
عن ابنتها.
In that process, she found out
وخلال تلك العملية، اكتشفت أن
that first, she was not alone.
أولًا, أنها لم تكن الوحيدة.
In the last year alone, 2013,
في آخر عام 2013 فقط،
6,000 people disappeared
6000 شخص اختفوا
in the state of Rio.
في ولاية "ريو".
But she also found out that in spite of that,
لكنها اكتشفت أيضًا إنه بالرغم من ذلك،
Rio had no centralized intelligence system
لا يوجد في "ريو" نظام تحقيق مركزي
for solving missing persons cases.
لحل قضايا الأشخاص المفقودين.
In other Brazilian cities, those systems
في مدن برازيلية أخرى، هذه الأنظمة
have helped solve up to 80 percent
ساعدت في حل أكثر من 80%
of missing persons cases.
من قضايا الأشخاص المفقودين.
She started a campaign,
بدأت بعمل حملة،
and after the secretary of security got 16,000 emails
وبعد أن استقبل وزير الأمن أكثر من 16 ألف بريدًا إلكترونيًا
from people asking him to do this,
من أشخاص يطلبون منه أن يفعل ذلك،
he responded, and started to build a police unit
استجاب وبدأ بإنشاء وحدة شرطية
specializing in those cases.
متخصصة في هذة القضايا.
It was open to the public at the end of last month,
وتم افتتاحها للعامة في آخر الشهر الماضي،
and Jovita was there
و"جوفيتا" كانت هناك
giving interviews and being very fancy.
تجري المقابلات وكانت مذهلة.
And then, there is Leandro.
والآن، هذا هو "ليوناردو".
Leandro is an amazing guy
"ليوناردو" فتى مذهل
in a slum in Rio,
في حي عشوائي في "ريو"،
and he created a recycling project in the slum.
قام بعمل مشروع إعادة تدوير في الحي.
At the end of last year, December 16,
وفي نهاية العام الماضي، 16 ديسمبر،
he received an eviction order
تلقى أمر إزالة
by the Rio de Janeiro state government
من حكومة ولاية "ريو دي جانيرو"
giving him two weeks to leave the space
مع مهلة أسبوعين لكي يغادر المكان
that he had been using for two years.
الذي استمر في استخدامه لمدة عامين.
The plan was to hand it over to a developer,
الخطة تم إعطائها لمطور،
who planned to turn it into a construction site.
الذي خطط ليصبح موقع بناء.
Leandro started a campaign using one of our tools,
"ليوناردو" بدأ بعمل حملة مستخدمًا أحد أدواتنا
the Pressure Cooker,
"حلة الضغط"،
the same one that Bia and Jovita used,
نفس الأداة التي استخدمتها "بيا" و"جوفيتا"،
and the state government changed their minds
وحكومة الولاية غيرت رأيها
before Christmas Eve.
قبل أعياد الميلاد.
These stories make me happy,
هذه القصص تجعلني سعيدة،
but not just because they have happy endings.
لكن ليس فقط لأن لها نهايات سعيدة.
They make me happy because they are
إنهم يجعلوني سعيدة لأنهم
happy beginnings.
بدايات سعيدة.
The teacher and parent community at Bia's school
مجتمع المدرس والآباء في مدرسة "بيا"
is looking for other ways they could improve
يبحثون عن طرق أخرى كي يستطيعوا تطوير
that space even further.
هذه المساحة أكثر.
Leandro has ambitious plans
لدي "ليوناردو" خطط طموحه
to take his model to other low-income communities in Rio,
أن ينقل نموذجه للمجتمعات ذات الدخل المنخفض الأخري في "ريو"
and Jovita is volunteering at the police unit
و"جوفيتا" تطوعت في الوحدة الشرطية
that she helped created.
التي ساعدت في إنشائها.
Bia, Jovita and Leandro
"بيا" و"جوفيتا" و"ليوناردو"
are living examples of something
يعيشون كنماذج لشيء ما
that citizens and city governments around the world
ذلك أن المواطنين وحكومات المدن حول العالم
need to know:
يحتاجوا أن يعلموا:
We are ready.
أننا مستعدون.
As citizens, we are ready
كمواطنين، نحن مستعدون
to decide on our common destinies,
لكي نقرر مصيرنا المشترك،
because we know that the way we distribute power
لأننا نعلم أن طريقة توزيعنا للسلطة
says a lot about how we actually value everyone,
تقول كثيرًا كيف نقدر الجميع،
and because we know
ولأننا نعرف
that enabling and participating in local politics
أن الإتاحة والمشاركة في السياسات المحلية
is a sign that we truly care
هي علامة على إننا حقًا نهتم
about our relations to one another,
بعلاقاتنا من شخص لآخر،
and we are ready to do this
وإننا جاهزون لفعل ذلك
in cities around the world right now.
الآن في المدن في جميع أنحاء العالم.
With the Our Cities network,
عن طريق شبكة مدننا،
the Meu Rio team
فريق "ميو ريو"
hopes to share what we have learned
يأمل أن يشارك ما تعلمناه
with other people who want to create
مع الأشخاص الآخرين الذين يريدون أن ينشئوا
similar initiatives in their own cities.
مبادرات مشابهة في مدنهم.
We have already started doing it in São Paulo
ولقد بدأنا في فعل ذلك في "ساو باولو"
with incredible results,
بنتائج لا تصدق،
and want to take it to cities around the world
ونريد أن ننقل التجربة إلى المدن حول العالم
through a network of citizen-centric,
من خلال شبكة المواطن - المركزي،
citizen-led organizations
المنظمات مدنية القيادة
that can inspire us,
التي يمكن أن تلهمنا،
challenge us, and remind us to demand
تتحدانا وتذكرنا لنطلب
real participation in our city lives.
المشاركة الحقيقية في حياة مدننا.
It is up to us
الأمر متروك لنا
to decide whether we want schools
لكي نقرر إذا كنا نريد مدارس
or parking lots,
أم ساحات انتظار للسيارات،
community-driven recycling projects
مشروعات إعادة تدوير مجتمعية
or construction sites,
أم مواقع بناء،
loneliness or solidarity, cars or buses,
الوحدة أو التضامن، السيارات أم الحافلات،
and it is our responsibility to do that now,
وإنها مسئوليتنا لكي نفعل ذلك الآن،
for ourselves, for our families,
من أجل أنفسنا، ومن أجل عائلاتنا،
for the people who make our lives worth living,
ومن أجل الناس الذين يجعلون لحياتنا قيمة،
and for the incredible creativity,
ومن أجل الإبداع الغير معقول،
beauty, and wonder that make our cities,
والجمال والروعة التي تجعل مدننا،
in spite of all of their problems,
بالرغم من كل المشاكل،
the greatest invention of our time.
الإختراع الأعظم في الوقت الحالي.
Obrigado. Thank you.
شكرًا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)